I think we decided to focus this
conversation around Zach's most recent
essay yep called kovat 19 a war broke
out in heaven mm-hmm and I was really
happy to read this because it was so
mythopoetic so mythological and because
I'm a sucker for that kind of language
and I also thought it was quite brave
because nobody's writing like that you
make the very strong statement that
there's a war in heaven and using this
strong eschatological terminology is
that am I saying that right and I was
thinking about why that was so powerful
and I was thinking about Leonard Cohen
and I was thinking about Bob Dylan and I
was thinking about how they're always
singing about the end of the world like
in some level like there's always this
flood that's gonna come and and and
there's a crack in everything and you
know things are get a slide in all
directions and all these sort of lines
from from popular music we're coming
into my mind which is very biblical in
some sense and that's probably one of
the reasons why I really appreciate
Zak's essay and it's also I think a
reason why other people might be quite
critical of it because the people once
want a more rational explanation for
what's happening and that kind of thing
not the ER essay was was not not
rational or reasonable but so could we
speak about that can we speak about why
you're using this kind of kind of
language and why it's important and why
I think I think your essay seems to be
making the rounds in other words it's
affecting people
in one way or another sure thank you I
mean I I'm still actually surprised by
the reception of the paper I'm
very happy I didn't expect it to be as
as well received as it was actually
because I mostly expected people to be
you know cautious or worried about the
mythopoetic angle but I mean I was
trying to draw attention it as clearly
as I could to the interior aspects of
the crisis too and to specifically have
something to say that wasn't directly
about the biology and the geopolitics
and all the dynamics that are within
this and yeah and some of it was also
just in my own experience returning to
where I go for solace right like as I
was looking out at the stuff that's
coming from like the spiritual crown you
know and just terrible a lot of it's
terrible like an insulting I think
insulting and a retreat to a kind of
relativistic pre tragic spiritual
escapism
so can you characterize that describe
what is so so terrible and then
something about you know let's say a
spiritual reaction to well I mean like
and again it it you know it's it's
complex because there's there's so much
in the religious landscape now right so
you still have the grip traditions you
know the church and and the Sangha and
all these things would still exist from
the great traditions I'm talking mostly
about the non-affiliated kind of human
potential movement New Age movement
crowd at least in America where there's
this strange confluence between
post-modernism and Buddhism and in
particular where you get this like
allegiance between the deconstructing of
truth by Kozma
which is something specific like
something specific and the
deconstructing of like experience of
self and reality in terms of some
discourses in Buddhism right and not
specifically Buddhism and most of the
people I'm talking about really haven't
even like read a Buddhist Sutra but what
they're getting is the notion that if
you analyze your own experience like of
a boss and a meditator you will realize
that most of the things you take to be
true or not simply true right that
there's some deeper reality beyond the
kind of given phenomenology so emptiness
different than form mostly we don't
experience I'm Dennis although even it's
always already there and then
post-modernism is doing something
specific in linguistics all right taking
aim at the modern notion of objectivity
and these other things and so you give
this confidence where you get a
relativistic post-modernism with a
particular brand of kind of spiritual
criticism of the kind of conventional
reality let's say it's the spiritual
criticism and so though you end up
getting people denying that viruses
exist right and that we have bodies and
any right / correct and thanking the
virus and writing a whole long things
where they end up saying that actually I
don't believe any of the things I'm
saying that's not right we shouldn't
believe anything you can't believe
anything we don't know anything but
here's a long Vista this list of things
I believe but I don't really believe
that and so there's a lack of courage
and spiritual fortitude on the part of
those people who are or are people are
looking to for that and so yeah it was
it's just concerning and it's of course
it's still still going on you know that
that kind of that kind of view so in
some sense this was a response to that I
was trying to you know as you say it's
not an unreasonable peace but I'm saying
the peace is not unreasonable and so
reasonable things about profound topics
instead of thinking that saying
something unreasonable is profound just
because it's unreasonable or not
unreasonable when me and John we're
talking the last time with Christopher
or master of Pietro in the midst of our
conversation I came up with this sort of
thing I said this is like a judgment or
something right what's happening it just
came into my mind right as a biblical
language and John was I was saying wait
a minute hold on here be careful
so maybe John you want to speak to to
the cut your cautionary sure a response
to the dangers of using this kind of
language and how can we use this kind of
poetic language correctly or rightly or
in a way that's helpful and I think Zach
did a great job of doing it I do
attitude so first of all compliment Zach
I read the article and I thought it was
exemplary of how to use what I would
call symbolic language in order to make
important bridges symbol on to connect
between the phenomenological and what we
might call the ontological because I saw
that a large part of what the essay was
doing was exactly using what you're
calling myth or poetic language to
bridge between those two domains for
people in a very powerful way and I
think that's very important we can talk
about that more as we go into our
discussion but I think that how do you
how do you get craft a language that's
you know deeply transgender that deeply
resonates with people's phenomenological
experience and yet also gives them you
know a way of articulating a grasp on
reality that is very needed right now
and I thought what Zach was doing was
exemplifying that very well that's how
it landed for me that that's how the
language was coming up the biblical and
so the biblical language
I've often cautioned people I think the
most appropriate attitude toward the
Bible is a deeply reverential
ambivalence the Bible is it is a
terrible book in the sense of its
capacity to cause great harm but also in
its terrific in the sense that it can
induce
significant powerful and transformation
in people so the biblical language my
concern is I share one with Zack and
then one that I think he might have also
I think he's he steered very very
adroitly between Scylla and Charybdis
they're very nicely
between a fundamentalist return of this
language because my concern is and I've
seen a lot of people talking this way
the virus is very much like an Old
Testament deity it's abstract it's
ubiquitous you don't know what it will
strike right it's it's demanding purity
codes from us it's narrowing our world
we feel like we're under judgment we
feel like we're being punished we feel
like we have to invoke purity codes and
this is a very ancient way of thinking
for us and it's very problematic I think
it would be very antithetical to the
direction that Zack is pointing to in
his paper in his article if we if that
kind of thing becomes prevalent and then
the alternative and I don't think it's
an exclusive alternative although the
culture pretends that they are the
alternative is is the kind of decadent
Romanticism that Zack put his finger on
that spirituality that lacks integrity
not only courage Zack I would say it
lacks integrity in that what it does is
it privileges certain kinds of discourse
well of course claiming that no
discourse has privilege it claims a kind
of exceptionalism for Buddhism that
people like Stephen bachelor and Evan
Thompson have just shown is without
merit as an argument it does a very poor
job opposite I would say to what you
were trying to do Zack and succeeding at
bridging between the phenomenology and
it doesn't set up an agave what it does
is it says all everything is to be
constructed in here everything is
deconstructed out there and therefore I
ultimately get some kind of nebulous
conformity between my inner world and my
outer world because they're all equally
deconstructed which is I think precious
I'm kind of irresponsible in a in a very
powerful way so I think I didn't I I saw
Jack
like I say steering between both of
those ways in which we could start using
I agree with Zack fundamentally on this
that when were in liminal right and
that's exactly what the phenomenology
and the ontology are in this like the
deep like talk to each other when we're
in liminal we are drawn towards this
kind of language I totally agree what
I'm suggesting is the what the we can be
drawn and then we can articulate and
appropriate that language in three
different ways at least to my mind one
is the one that Zack is very critical of
and I am too a sort of decadent
romanticism that has that purely
negative and I think vacuous conformity
and then there's a kind of
fundamentalism that I think especially
when we're enacting purity codes is a
very real danger and you know and the
attendant things upon it you know
conspiracy theory scapegoating before
all things we have to be very very
careful of and so I thought that what
Zack did was from and perhaps act this
is one of the reasons why it's it's
getting such a great reception I think
you in addition to the content which I
think was valuable I think you
exemplified a way of appropriating this
language that as I again I agree with
you is what is going to emerge as the
response to the attempt to symbol on to
connect the phenomenological logical and
you steered it between the two things
that I'm most concerned of well I have
three there were two I've articulated
one is the fundamentalism the other is
you know like you say the completely
decadent romantic magical thinking
I would put it I'm using that
term technically right and then the
third one I have a fear of which you
also didn't do you very great care of
which is a kind of pretentious utopian
certainty well you know this clearly
indicates that the revolution should
come and this is a blah blah blah blah
right and that kind of thing too and it
right and and and and and there's a
danger of course around apocalyptic
thinking to fall into that kind of
utopic pseudo certainty and I think you
shared between all three of those really
really well so
that's why there's sorry to drop maybe
there's also a danger of sort of with
this eschatology is life hating or
something it's like you want the
apocalypse to happen
well that overlaps a lot with the
fundamentalism fundamentalism tends to
you know you know the emphasis is on the
the destructive nature of God's wrath
and in it
that's usually bound up with a kind of
conspiratorial there's all the evil ones
out there that I resent and hate and I'm
afraid of and this will finally get rid
of them and those of us who are pure
will be set free to the earth that kind
of thing and the and the fundamentalist
view and that's called the the new-age
view there are actually isomorphic in
their structure like yes yeah there
there's a there's a basically kind of a
structural narcissism yes and a tendency
to project and basically it stands of
like mind or faith only which ends up
being you create your reality kind of
thing or basically you get what you
deserve yes and so that's yeah that's
just there and as a cognitive
developmental psychologist it's easy to
see the places and people's
personalities where they can actually
retreat to lower forms of meaning making
and self regulation so so you allowed it
to that very clearly when you talked
about the possibility of losing the
world's soul and falling in with this
type in I just wanted to unpack that a
little bit because I thought you were
implying and and just to add to that
also tragic you talked about the tragic
and maybe that's a remedy to this New
Age thinking is for us to really
contemplate the tragic right yeah I
think of John as you were speaking I was
thinking of this phrase by Harbor moss
it was something like cuz you know he
brought his dissertation on shelling and
the problem of free will and then later
in his life habermas returned to
Kierkegaard and began to consider
religion again very seriously and in
this later work he talked about the the
untapped semantic potentials of
while Gorge that third there lay within
religious language and and symbol
untapped semantic potential specifically
and then this is it to think for
protecting vulnerable forms of community
life and experience so the idea being
that the meaning that lies hidden within
these symbolic ways of speaking it has
to do with the basis of choice making
and relationship and ethics Frank which
is also another difference between I
think what I was trying to do and what
is usually happening under the spiritual
kind of rhetoric which is that we need
to inform the basis of ethics and choice
not the basis of emotional
self-regulation and the feeling of
safety base of a and self-esteem
gratifications right so those are
distinct and the mind wants to do bother
like you want to create a sense of
meaning in a worldview that makes you
feel safe and makes you feel valuable
and important and in control and but you
also want to create one that allows you
to live in relationship to reality and
specifically the reality that you have
other people and and so yeah I was
trying to really bring home something
like in an ethos and and the sense of
you know for lack of a better word
morality which is relevant now which is
why I was concerned about what we're
able to say on a hospital ward in New
York City right like one of the things
get that can be said in these places and
how important that must be right able to
say the right things to people who are
actually suffering not people who are
afraid of suffering and trying to
reconcile themselves and the calm their
limbic system after looking at Facebook
for an hour and a half people who are in
the midst of it and where are the
cultural resources we can use in the
languages that are available in the
symbols that are shared between us
can be with one another in the the
intensity of this and say something so
that's kind of where where it came from
and then I ended up returning to my
roots in Emerson and other places where
I was looking for this this kind of
language so and also just to my
background in music you know I think
often about this triplet kid I got from
Forrest Landry which is song text and
code P in different forms of expression
and that all of them are important and
code is about what you do so let it be
written so let it be done like a legal
code right and text is about this
interest objective clarity of semantics
basically precision song is different
song is rooted and subjective and this
is where symbol and image lives so much
and so connecting song with text is what
I was trying to do
well not cuz I'm not right about the
facts and legal code and the quarantine
and how the keeper saw I wasn't good to
him in there I was just trying to
connect with the song that I was trying
to sing and finding a way to bring that
up into some space of reason and what
you're talking about is poetry you know
correct right and and and a need for
that right but the problem of just
invoking poetry again is in poetry
because of you know several generations
and education has been relegated to a
certain status and function with another
culture but I think is not I not
attributing this to you Andrew but I'm
saying how most people knew when most
people hear the word poetry they don't
hear what's that for yeah that's true
yeah right they don't and that's why
there's a huge educational thrust
towards the end of Zach's article but I
wanted to pick up on something first
before I do want to turn to the
educational stuff because I think it's
really important so if the first point
you were saying about that Zach is the -
um this goes to where Chris and I have
been doing about trying to remember that
when we invoke the language the sacred
has both the homing and the horror
aspects to it right at the point of the
sacred yes is if it's supposed to
shelter us but it's also supposed to
expose us to
a reality that is beyond us that's the
numinous side of things and I think the
really difficult thing that we have to
do right now with the symbolic language
is write its effect because it's
ultimately sacred language is to craft
it in such a way that those two things
are being done at the same time that
we're giving people a sense of how they
can get grounded and centered but also
challenge them to face the
transformative demands that reality is
placing upon us and I think that's
another concern I have is a polarization
of the language of the sacred either
into the oh it's you know it's all
wonderful we're all snuggly and warm and
we all love each other or or or you know
which is also becoming the sort of
horrific nihilism with its you know
we're all just doomed and destroyed in
sort of glorying in a way that reality's
overwhelming because I can see some
people finally finding but in a deeply
shadowed twisted way you know well
finally I'm finally connected back to
reality right you know at least there's
this horrific thing that's destroying
you know all the offices and
institutions of power and let yes and
you know that kind of fist shaking
salute towards the flames and so part of
the difficulty I think we face here is
to craft language they can bring those
two sides of its sacred together again
one of my favorite one of my favorite
versions of this Wilfred was for
children so it's an edgy as an
educational impact on it is in the
Narnia Chronicles and their kids are
talking and they're talking to some of
the talking animals and they say well is
at Joslin came and the kids go and the
animals go oh no no he's not hey hmm but
he's good right and there was this right
and it was there was a Lewis is trying
to get this other place right again we
you can see the sacred as not the team
you know I will be what I will be you
know God's self naming right but also
the fact that this is ultimately
something that affords transformation
and transcendence in a powerful way and
so you'll give me one more minute guys I
know I'm talking a lot this brings me to
this ongoing discussion I've been having
with Jordan Hall and Christmas DiPietro
and Geiss and stock and with you and is
this whole notion of what you were
pointing to in your major point a minute
ago Andrew sorry Zack it was that right
that you're trying to link this language
to being able to say the right thing and
do the right it's ultimately you're
trying to link it to wisdom in my in my
language and this fear you're a party
and care right well but that's a big
part the rationality of caring is what
Socrates was primarily about above and
beyond any rationality of argumentation
he makes that very clear the one thing
he knew was Tata he knew how to properly
care and what to care about and how to
care but that Britta but the invoking
Socrates brings up this whole thing I've
been trying to talk about this notion of
faith Socratic faith because the
relationship to symbols is not one of
conviction in the sense and of the way
in which the argument convict's you
neither should be and zack is critical
of this just kind of an emotional
affective response that's an
inappropriate response to symbols i mean
so my tutor here is Tillich that the
appropriate response to symbol is faith
but faith completely understood not as
this magical projection and willful
assertion or passive
you know acceptance of you know some
fatalistic demon but more again this
ability to what Zack is again I think
exemplifying in his paper which is to
sense the Kairos sense the course of
things and become deeply coupled and
involved with it and I think that is
something that needs to be talked about
and it's also something that we can
offer people now as an alternative to
either magical faith or you know merely
sort of assertion or faith and I think
that's also something that needs to be
brought into this discussion and I think
is that again I don't think this is
foreign to your article Zack I think you
you're clearly exemplifying it in in
what you're talking about and the way
you're invoking the symbol
language almost in a prophetic fashion I
totally want I just want to repeat what
you said about the importance maybe of
joining those two worlds together right
that the the the horror and and the fate
that's what I am and if we if we're just
in the sublime blissful world of
imagination it's nice but we never come
down to the earth and if we're there
just in in this sort of materialistic
horror you don't have any vision so it's
it's bringing these two worlds together
I think that's exactly and what I'm
saying is that act of bringing them
together is of course inherently
symbolic I keep saying symbol on is to
join together across the limit all right
and that because you're confronting the
liminal you're confronting those both
you know the the prospect and the refuge
and I think what gives you that I think
is this kind of faith that I'm talking
about now and it's a it's a faith that
in my opinion and and I argue it's more
than my opinion who cares about my
opinion my arguments are that that
notion of faith is deeply interwoven
with this more extended Socratic notion
of rationality and the wisdom project
that I think exact is invoking in the
pedagogical part of his article
beautiful gasps I mean there's so many
directions to go now like I'm wondering
what Andrew what what did you have in
mind what comes to mind for me is this
notion of the the post tragic and the
notion I was thinking of the future I
was thinking of the prophetic and and
the future and how we use symbols
because we can't really understand
what's going on in the immediacy of
what's happening so we use symbols as
kind of a vehicle to take us towards the
future is that does that ring true in
any kind of a way or um does does I mean
that's you know
[Applause]
the word that came to mind now is a
where the Ken Wilber corn which is mom
Dalek thinking which he was talking
about when the I of mind contemplates
spirit right when the I of spirit
contemplates peered you just have spirit
when the I have mine come to plate
spirit you get this strange language
which is a kind of symbolic language the
mandala quite a light language where
you're working with image and symbol in
a very intense way I write I talk about
the thoughts of the heart in the paper
in this notion of the thoughts of the
heart yes comes from James James Hillman
and this is the the language I was
trying to use the language that is which
is the language of care right which is
Socrates is language if yep when he has
that confidence that he could show up
with any interlocutor and be able to use
his words to express and kind of create
the thoughts of the heart between them
into this is this isn't this is a true
sense of philosophy I think that's
working with working with the thoughts
of the heart essentially and it's not
science technically right and it's not
logic and argument in the in a strict
sense but it's also not illogical and
irrational or based on just phenomenal
experience or ecstatic experience or
those kind of things so it's this hybrid
language like you're saying which which
brings the two together and then it can
take the particular take the best of
science and does not contradict that
and it can take the best of the mystical
and the purely prophetic and those
things and bring them together and good
and thoughts of the heart are the most
universal thoughts and forms of language
and so they are a kind of common sense
if I can use that way of speaking but
they do sometimes end up being cloaked
in things that look like traditional
religious forms of language and so
that's I find the biggest trick now
when I'm working with these modalities
is to not basically offend the
scientists right one issue and then the
other issue is not to to make it complex
enough that you don't get it confused
that's just being New Age all right so
you don't want to you don't want to
offend the scientists who dismiss you as
being fundamentalists or something and
then you also don't want to attract a
bunch of people who are actually looking
for something much simpler just to
gratify their ego needs for safety and
control justice a new age market coerce
and so that's the death dance and yeah
I'm just kind of overwhelmed actually
the key to getting the the the praise
for the paper I read wasn't I wasn't
expecting it but yeah so that's what one
of the things that came to mind there
and then as I was saying this notion of
that the sacred includes the kind of
terrifying and that is also that with
this notion of the post tragic being
extremely important some have talked
about in a few podcasts and the idea of
being that when tragedies there he it
must be lived through yeah it can't be
avoided and dealing with it actually it
doesn't mean fixing it or making the
tragic disappear dealing with it
actually means finding a way to have it
and more and I talked about what is
within illness and what is within death
that unravel it from the inside which is
to say as hospice workers know and
health care workers now and I've been
I've been a caregiver for many years in
my life and that there is what's the
right way to say it
you know yeah so I'll use symbolic
language right which is that God
we'll catch you it's something like that
is that you there's nowhere you can fall
where you fall outside of God right
something like that and and that
includes all of the horror right that
God is within that darkness and so yeah
so so again it's not about being stuck
in the tragedy and saying oh it's just
horror right as I know it is horror but
humans can withstand our they and humans
are made in the midst of tragedy so so
much of history has been humans making
personhood in the midst of tragedy and
so again the untapped semantic potential
of religious language is for protecting
vulnerable forms of human life these are
the things we've done to be together and
with glad hearts in the midst of tragedy
that's where the Bible is interesting
because it is so political so political
slavery and freedom and unjust ends
there's all of these stories of people
in intense and plagues of course people
in intense intense interconnectedness
and so so yeah it's not abstract in many
cases the Bible's just there and and so
yeah there's that there's that encoding
and human experience of making meaning
and personhood in the midst of tragedy
and and so that's just I'm saying when
we're bringing these languages together
you know to what end it's because I
think in part of that need to create the
new religion right this new form of
religiosity would be it's coming at us
again now at a higher register that
demand from the world that's saying look
at look at the suffering of the pain
that's unfolding and how do we come
together in the midst of this and it's
about what we're trying to do here in a
sense with the creation of a new a new
renew resources of symbol
language for meaning-making yeah because
maybe the guy in in the hospital in New
York doesn't have time for figuring
things out in a very reductive way he
just wants the truth and the truth has
to be deep right it can't be superficial
or or and and I guess the kind of God
you're speaking of you know this is
their that and that contains both the
darkness and the light or both the
horror and and the beauty so it's like
you don't want one you don't want to
split those two you want you if you're
on your deathbed I imagine I've never
been on my deathbed but you would want
things to be as close to the bone and it
is true as as possible and I often
religious language may be the only way
to to express that I don't know well or
the heart spoken as directly as possible
but but the thing is it has to take yeah
that's the thing I mean there's nothing
worse than these words being spoken and
they don't take for the person right
indeed that's what I'm trying to get out
with this this notion of faith where
it's again not willful assertion not
magical thinking are not claiming to
know things that you don't actually have
any claim to know it's not a pretense of
certainty it's not all the things that
we sort of pretend faith is no it's a
it's rather the sense there's a beauty
and I don't mean a a pleasure because
beauty can be terrifying
Rilke reminds us of that repeatedly but
there's a beauty to these symbols for
people
there's they're they have a receptivity
that's what I'm trying to get at so that
they take the symbols take they catch
they write today they join the worlds
together they they afford aspiration
they call the person to the depths that
you're putting your finger on Andrew I'm
really interested in that by the way I
want to point out you know when Socrates
was doing his thing
Athens was literally under siege from
without and there had literally been a
devastating plague in the city so
Socrates is not also know
figure that is somehow you know abstract
in the ivory power you know well we are
in the midst of pestilence and killing
with each fact we're all of you know
everything well many of the dialogues
are actually even historically set and
that in that time period so Socrates is
completely apropos for the situation
we're in but when I'm interested in and
is is good well I invoked him and
because I he seemed to be able to do
that he seemed to be yellow like Zack
said he can he could adjust himself to
the interlocutor he had the faith of
being able to show up and he had the
faith that he could say things that
would take that people would you know
that you know the that would tempt them
towards the good that would call them to
their deaths
and what's interesting to me what's
what's the difference and I think this
is ultimately what I want to really get
to with Zack stop was what's the
educational background that makes people
capable of appropriately being called by
these symbols so that they take and
they're operationally viable to them and
people who where it falls dead on their
chest it's just empty words or they get
all of the stuff we're critical all of
you know the the willful assertion
magical thinking senses of how to
misappropriate the sometimes that that's
for me where this is the knife-edge
question that's coming down how do we
what do we give to people how do we
adduce how do we draw forth from them
this capacity for this kind of faith
where what I mean by faith is to be
caught up in the the terrible beauty of
this symbol so that one is called to
one's depth and one is drawn out
aspirationally into the depths of the
world so that one can confront the
deepest things with the deepest
resources at ones disposal that for me
is the central question that I think
well that's forgive me Zack that's what
I saw the paper as really driving
towards at the end
no no that's such a good question such a
good set of questions right cuz it's cuz
this is what what's the termite pearls
before swine
right yeah it's like and this is a
classic educational problem which is
that there's there's there's a depth to
like a you know an ancient text which
you know you wonder the level of
maturity of the reader that's needed to
actually perceive the depth and so we
get what are the prerequisites in
personality and character structure and
cognition and other things to be able to
receive the symbol that's there and -
yeah it's a it's a that's the well
there's two things I distantly come to
mind you know one is experiences
formative experiences where the same
symbol or comparable symbols or
modalities of expression were terrible
for you right so many of the people I
know who find it hard to be receptive to
the language in an article like to my
Road you know had and I think we
mentioned this last time we spoke John
they had bad experiences in their in
their youth right yeah a different kind
of yeah that happened to use
this kind of simple thing and so so
that's one major important element there
which is that like this stuff's been
given a bad name you know and there's a
way that it's like the wells been
poisoned and so how do we make it clear
that we're drawing from a clear spring
that it's a different source and so
that's why many people leave there they
go to the yeast right door they go from
the east to the west and depending on
where you're where you're from so that's
I think one component so there's a part
of it which means it's something about
like either making them explicit I'm
working it through
or finding a novelty a real novelty than
the way the things are expressed so
that's that's the issue there other than
the other the other component that came
to mind has to do with element of
practice and modeling yeah which is like
have you ever seen someone in your
actual presence do that then right have
you experienced an elder or a teacher
truly being inspired by ideas and I
think John this is why your work is so
magnetic right because you're modeling
for people what it's like to do what
you're asking them to do you're showing
that like this is what it's like to be
taken into the matrix of the symbol and
live in it and and work with it the
power that comes from that yeah and
faith in the life of ideas and that kind
of thing so another thing that is clear
that when people see it when they
actually see it they knit is magnetic
and people move towards that this is a
question of which points in their lives
and especially formative phases of
adolescent identity formation and an
adult like these key phases who or the
different spokespeople there for these
things and are they getting at the right
times such that when they need it
they'll be able to turn to it yeah for
solace and and the final one I think is
really that this notion of practice just
a little bit deeper which is that it
takes sustained attention to reap the
rewards of this kind of emotion and
identity configuration so to the degree
that we are becoming as a culture
systemically fragmented in our attention
it's gonna be hard for us to actually
sustain the focus to have a complex
enough relationship to the symbol and
the accompanying kind of like Semantic
Web to get to get drawn in and to get
empowered I am again so so that's that's
key and that's not just about meditation
it's about long-form books and other
things that
defragment the attention and allow you
to walk you just read for two hours
almost straight now you're so deep in
the language that when it starts to move
with symbolism you can actually get the
full range of connotations that are
implied instead of the soundbite like
tweet version right and anything that's
a soundbite tweet of anything that's not
gonna end up having that symbolic depth
and richness that is necessary so so
that's another component I think in
terms of the kind of pedagogical look at
just how can we do this and make people
more susceptible to head to these
resources that they were in that they
become available
just just one thing I'd like to sort of
add to that it seems to me that in the
present crisis that we're going through
and also just to bring it back to the
crisis our reaction to the crisis sort
of depends on how deeply we have studied
these these things or how deeply we've
studied life and if we've studied them
deeply we know that there's a crisis all
the time right this is not this is an
exceptional crisis in one sense but the
fact that we're all gonna die is it's
like that's like the first thing you
learn right and if you study any kind of
religious tradition is to contemplate
the fact that there's a crisis going on
all the time just by virtue of the fact
that we have bodies that are
disintegrating and we have to live that
tragedy yeah I think that's right I mean
I think I think it was when I was
talking with Peter limber again his
online stoah about and I want to connect
this to Zak's point about long-form
attention because I think deal logos and
what we're doing here is also a great
exemplification of that long-form
attention that is deeply enmeshed with
trying to draw forth you know a new
fountain intelligibility from all of
these hidden semantic and conceptual
resources so I think that's why idea the
logos is actually crucial and the logos
is not just
presentation of idea the logos is an
exemplification as accent all the way of
life and how it is actually viable for
people being enacted right here right
now I think what I wanted to say about
you the point you made Andrew is
connected to this long-form practice you
know that it's it's um so stoicism one
way Visser does this and beyond faith
you know that our word fatal which we
attack we we don't we now equate with
causing death that's not its origin his
origin is having to do with fate which
is the way in which reality acts beyond
all of our ego centric projects and
concerns in the way which we can be
struck by absurdity or tragedy there's
many different ways in which reality
hits us in the face and says aha you
have all your projects and all your
narcissistic narrative but look
Here I am right and so yeah there why
the associate EK most wrong right is of
course the event of death is the most in
that sense fatal it's the one that makes
us most aware of how reality is involved
and beyond us but then the point is not
and I think this is what you're saying
and ER the point is not to be
considerate just considerate of the the
fact that our existence will terminate
it's that right here right now we are
meshed in fatality and the mortality of
all things because always always
everything is threatening us in the way
that it is always beyond our narrative
and are narcissistic narrative and we've
had up we've we're going into a culture
that is doubling down and trying to sort
of no no no no I can just make it so I
can just make it so by speaking it more
loudly and getting other people to show
it with me
and so I think that gives us that's back
again and I'm not trying to like Dragoon
something but I think that's again this
sense of sacredness of sacredness is to
be at home with right at home with your
mortality and the fatality of all things
while never denying it's real horror the
fact that it can always it's always
every moment capable of showing you in
absurdity or in horror
or in what's happened you know in terror
or in all kinds of things that reality
is something that is always always
always and you know not always just in
the long term but always always here and
now beyond us in very very powerful ways
and so stoicism was a lot about trying
to we order yet and right and and I
think socialism as a clear example comes
out of the Socratic tradition very
clearly in which people were trying to
Wed Socratic rationality with this kind
of faith
stoicism has been called a religion and
I think not unfairly because of the way
in which you tried to get people right a
new sense of the sacred that allowed
them right to deal with the
moment-by-moment fatality of all things
I think the good is amiss probably do
something very similar which is why
there's often comparisons drawn between
stoicism and Buddhism by the way so I
think it's really really important what
Andrew just said and connect it to what
Zacks said and I think what connects
them is this whole thing we've been
talking about this this sense this lived
viable aspirational sense of the sacred
right here right now great and just
maybe after we've said all that we've
talked about that this is being the
state that we're in or all the time
maybe I want maybe we could move to
speak about what you called you call
something great on patterning or
transition or what's actually happening
now and I don't mean about the virus in
any literal sense
I mean what's what's I mean yes literal
because it is a literal thing but maybe
what's going on now what's going on in
time because you talk about historicity
I think Zack and and and the importance
of that and the importance of time and
is my question clear it is and yeah I
mean fate is unfolding
and we're in kind of sacred Kairos right
where reality is where reality is
appearing kind of again as it were
because of our the deep simulations that
were produced by the civilization as it
was moving through where we thought that
we didn't need to have massive supplies
back loaded in hospitals just in case
there was a Mike we didn't think that
through right because we were deep in a
simulation and everything was fine and
so now yeah we are confronting reality
and so the question is yeah will we will
we pull together like Stoics and love
fate and end up in crazy and and and
moving with our identities to become to
become one with the tragic situation
then transform it somehow from the
inside in response to it and so that's I
see mostly what's unfolding now and
that's why I talked about a war in
heaven is that Jude's choice it's about
the basis of choice and who are we
choosing to be and so that's this
conflict between these ideals we have of
ourselves right are we stepping into
that so what is the war of heaven
between who and who is it between the
knee list and let's say the the life
hater and the life giver I mean it's
what is the war what is it's me it's
Matt it's massively complicated right
you remember last time we spoke it was
this sense of the divine double and then
we kind of brought home one and the room
was like no it's actually there's many
of those potential selves that are in
your arc typical imagination to move
towards us like personal ideals yeah and
so what's happened now with the great on
patterning is that everyone's sitting at
home with a lot of time were an absence
of time so a fragmentation of conti the
way you're hanging out with many many of
yourselves who usually don't get a lot
of airtime
right so there's many of these
archetypal personalities and
possibilities for yourself
are now flooding the imagination into
this opening from being unpadded and so
it happens when you travel it happens
other times in your day-to-day life when
something like if you went for an
appointment that didn't happen and now
you've got like an hour to just sit
there and you don't have your phone or
something like what happened your
imagination goes unless you're a Penn
Stater
right like so there's the war in heaven
is that it's this is a universal version
of that of like being in the doctor's
office you know waiting for the
appointment and then what happens right
right and what happens in the doctor day
we're waiting for the appointment in the
doctor's office were nervous there's no
good magazines we're sitting there and
there's all of these different possible
cells that were thinking about them
because the way the world will be on the
other side of this is also unclear it
means that we're getting in touch with
all of all ourselves the full range
right shadow and light if I can use that
kind of polarization so it's not a war
between two forces it's a war between
the many potent possibilities of
ourselves that we're going to actualize
through really unique moments of choice
in the coming months right and so it's
about that so who do we choose to be
when we make a choice and and so again
it means we have the opportunity to
become incredible people right that's
one possibility we have the possibility
to be integral and to act with character
and integrity and to know the principles
that we want to live by and to live by
them more so now than ever because you
know rehearsals over these on time and
we have space are they yeah these are
the important choices so we have that
possibility which is rare actually to be
in a moment of historical gravitas where
you have the chance to be doing really
the right thing so but we also have the
opportunity to descend into
ass and through fragmentation of choice
and being many different people not
holding together with integrity and
catering to those voices that are most
selfish and most fear driven etc so
that's that balance that battle in our
personalities basically as we're faced
with decisions we never thought we'd
have to make in choices goods is that we
never even kind of thought were on the
table or now on the table so so that's
that's kind of how you know it's kind of
how I'm feeling it so the title of
Tillich's book the courage to be sort of
middle mind when you say that when we
mmm-hmm it was very clear about is that
required a transformation right in faith
and a transformation in the notion of
God you had to get to the God beyond the
God of theism we had to let the symbol
change which is part of what I wanted to
bring that you know the the ultimately
you know they're part of what this means
is is a participatory stance not not
neither you know you know a sort of
passive stance or an assertive stance
it's a participatory stance we have to
participate in this because we have to
be willing to let the symbols change too
and I think that was a very clear
message and and faith isn't the holding
on of to the existing symbol for Tillich
and it's cert and it's not any premature
closure right oh now I have it right
it's instead but it's the vector off the
Hebrew word right it's like the way you
have the way you're faithful to your
partner is not hold her that's why speak
I'm straight so I'm just using myself as
an example not to hold her now you
always have to be this way or you know
this here's a particular symbol I've
created for a relationship and you know
it's not up for negotiation that's it
like no that's not what it means it
means you have to be willing to be
involved and let yourself change as the
symbol change
so that you made it make maintain a
continuity of contact about it
and that brings me up to a concern with
what not with what Zack said because I
think what he said but I think there's
an extra dimension to the war in heaven
and you know Chris and I our work are
thinking about this and this also goes
to work that your your your harness is
talking about need hauser
the fact that many people when they and
Hahn talks about this too right when
people are throwing into this empty time
right they have and I'm trying not to be
insulting here but this is sort of a way
of getting the gist of they have a kind
of shallowness in imagination if you'll
allow me to use Corbin's idea they have
a merely imaginary sense of the
imagination not an imaginal they have a
purely subjective sense of the
imagination not a trans jacket one and
therefore it cuts them off in the very
way they have been in cultured to deal
with their imagination right it cuts
them off from the aspirational project
that we're talking about here and so my
concern is that they you know are sort
of Cartesian the subjectivity is being
challenged really dramatically here but
I'm concerned that people in order to
let the symbol in order to grow with the
symbol as it grows you have to have an
imaginal sense of the symbol not a
merely imaginary sense of it but the the
symbol and the image doesn't it's not in
your head space that's not ready
fundamentally between you and the world
it's a joining of you to something
deeply other than you and that means you
only know you're going to it when it's
actually transforming you and changing
you and that means transforming how it
appears and shines into you and I think
so my concern to put it in a phrases
right do we have the proper you know
training in the imaginal that will
afford us you know appropriating this
Kairos in the right way that's sorry I
keep circling back to this because this
I mean this is sort of my Socratic
concern it's like I'm trying to get
we're trying to act as midwife what
midwives but I think there's just
tremendous difficulties in the grammar
of our thought and discourse that
prevent us from tapping those semantic
resources that harbor Nawab Ramos and I
think Tillich we're trying to put their
finger up and that's why Zach's idea of
a total revolution of education is so
important I think I think that's I think
that that has I'm trying to strengthen
the case for that point yeah unless
unless like any purely individualistic
you know you know you know within my own
home I look like of course people have
to do that and I'm not you know but if
if if there's any sense in which that's
going to be sufficient for grieving our
way and is firing our way through this
Kairos that has to be really challenged
and I think I'm trying to I'm trying to
put an argument in here that actually
strengthens Zach's point yeah radical
right transformation is needed to our
educational system where you know it's
it's the line between education and an
acculturation is completely being
blurred it seems to me and what zach is
proposing and we've got to get back to
that unique powerful way you know just
before Zach you respond I I was thinking
about the fact that when you paint that
picture John it looks very very grim but
at the same time at the same time it is
grim and it is a grim picture at the
same time maybe a few individuals doing
this properly can go a long way right
and so I think of it again I think in
the biblical Ark story are like building
an ark or just you know building the
thing doing the thing properly now just
a few people can can save save the world
if I can be as she's right yeah no it's
not it's not cheesy I never understood
the etymology of that insult I love
cheese ever Fred's
and the weapons and he's the gadfly for
the entire place right and you know and
all these movements start up around him
and all the socratic low guy you know of
the all that you wish it's like it's
like you know it's like yeah it's the
Leonard Cohen II it's like he sank
beneath your wisdom like a stone
although he was Jesus but all the
ripples just spread out in like and that
was deeply deep and eventually it leads
to stoicism and Marcus Aurelius right we
I yes I do want to sorry exactly
commending you from speaking but I just
want to pick up on although in painting
a grim picture I keep holding out the
these exemplary figures and how in
situations very very similar to ours
they were able to enact and afford that
kind of educational enculturation 'el
reform that zach is pointing to so this
is this is not in an event it's this is
not an inevitable reminisce of doom or a
grimness of inevitable doom that's not
what I'm arguing for at all I'm arguing
for taking it very seriously but
pointing out there's real historical
examples of ways in which this can be
seen through right I think you know and
I mean I completely agree of course that
that the route here is something like
education extremely broadly construed or
there the word idea which is the word I
used in my book which is a word that
basically roughly means like the
intergenerational transmission that
keeps a polity together yeah so and that
is sorely lacking
thanks to like the exhaustion of the
modern school systems and now those
school systems have been shut off
basically all around the world and all
of the kids are at home and so it's it's
really an unprecedented situation
educationally and you know the question
of in what ways after this could we
change education so that a situation
like this doesn't occur again is the
question that I'm asking because so much
of the situation with kind of breakdown
of anything like a public sphere and the
kind of polarization
strewth culture and much of this also
rooted in the educational crisis broadly
construed so yeah and enculturation and
schooling were basically separated and
then we forgot to work on inculturation
anymore
and we taught kids a bunch of technical
skills to try to prepare them for jobs
early in modernity that was okay because
the churches were still going and
convenience we're still going and the
system hadn't basically colonized the
life world to the extent that the dinner
table wasn't a place of acculturation
anymore but separating those having
schooling going strong getting lots of
really technically capacitated people
through a school system up into some
extensive meritocracy right and then
alongside that lack of rich character
building inculturation old processes
right instead something like popular
culture and consumerism being the main
modality of toleration and so that's a
that's a nightmare and that's produced
the generations now that are in power
and aspiring to power so yeah they're
all of these cascades systematically
from educational failures and not just
failures of school and like TV could
have been different if you read the
early literature in the history of
Education when TV was coming out people
were talking about the way we were
talking about the internet in like 1995
or 2000 this is the thing that will save
democracy and television will do that
and like didn't pan out that way for a
number of reasons
so we failed across the board in using
the infrastructures and that technology
is we had to make the Padilla strong
enough to support the polity and so the
polity is in crisis and were realizing
the paucity of the pedido
which means we're realizing the that
fourfold educational crisis I broke down
last time is unfolding so my sense is
that if we move quickly we could in a
generation start to change things but it
would require some of the social
miracles I'll I have in my book which
are on the table now things like basic
income guarantee
and adult education right where that
where we could get a whole group of
people actually a whole generation of
like food service workers basically who
may or may not have jobs to return to we
could get them into position to become
more like teachers or community guides
working in a decentralized educational
system as opposed to returning them to
their jobs right but if we just try to
reboot the schools as we knew them and
kind of go back to the way it was I
think that's actually a recipe for
deepening the mental health crisis I
think we're gonna have to basically
address what's happening with the
immediate reforms of schooling on the
other side of it similar to what you'd
have to do after a war transpired like
yeah we'd have to find a way to help the
help the generations make sense of it
together and figure out a shared vision
for what it's like moving forward and
that's that's an educational an
educational challenge it's one of the
more profound ones we've faced so we're
looking at something like as different
from the schools we've had as the
schools we have are as different from
the ones we had before the first world
wars right and that difference in
America at least is profound like you're
looking at almost like one room
schoolhouse stuff for most of the
country in 1900s and then in 1950 you've
got these huge high schools that were
basically massive innovations so I'm
suggesting similarly now we're gonna
mean that much thinking about the
educational and psychological and
cultural dimensions of this as we are
thinking about you know biometric
infrastructures and economic stimulus
packages and geopolitical security and
those things are important but if we
just pretend that the culture will take
care of itself and education will be
fine the way it was then we'll repeat
the mistake you may not be exactly
identical but there will be a breakdown
because of the failure of
intergenerational transmission so I'm
getting the the massive you know
paradigm shift change in education needs
to happen
on one hand and then the other hand the
image he uses that is there is the
kitchen table or the you know so I like
that I think I think getting back to the
table and you know I know my daughter is
home studying and she's sitting around
the table doing her school and it's
wonderful it's like she's not corralled
into the into this sort of alienating
classroom kind of thing and she's much
more relaxed and just as a person person
person exactly you and you guys are I
think you're trying to say the local and
there needs to be a universal change and
a local change simultaneously oh yeah
those are related and you you know
you're lucky like to have a table to sit
around I know there's a lot of kids in
the United States for whom not being
able to go to school is sucks
yeah the parents are abusive there's not
enough room in the house and school was
actually the safe place for them mm-hmm
so I'm not like wanting to return it to
the family or even to the local
community per se because there's a
parochialism that can happen there there
was something innovative about the
universality okay so it's a hybrid and
again I expressed it in my book but but
yeah right now for many people they're
realizing holy crap like education was
taken out of the house like education
was taken from us my kids are taken from
me everyday like they're gonna realize
that when it's going well and you're
lucky and the table can be a place where
love happens in those things there may
be a realization and some quarters that
you know Wow many of those patterns that
have been in place that we take for
granted almost like they're a part of
nature are in fact not they have been
constructed and are now changing rapidly
so I do see on the horizon pretty
radical changes in the educational
possibilities yeah I do because one
place where Zach's notion of the
education crisis and my idea of the
meeting crisis came together of course
was in when I talked about what happens
after the personal information you have
the separation of the knowledge
institution from the wisdom institution
universities get separated from the
monasteries
and I was gonna say Andrew it's not just
that education was taken I would have
the the kitchens also taking up to the
church I was young enough that I went to
actually went to Sunday school it was
actually called Sunday school and and
and you know and the problem with that
is Sunday school is what is was a very
degenerate version of what you know what
the monasteries once were was basically
indoctrination right and once you've got
the child sort of to memorize the
doctrines but even there you saw that
for some people into something and I'm
thinking what the monasteries have been
and how they are in other cultures like
you know the Buddhist monastery is not
separate in the way that it was
separated from the knowledge institution
disagreed it is for example in the West
or something like that so what I'm
trying to get at again is this idea that
we not only need to change the but I
think this is part of what Zak is saying
too so I don't want to say sound like
I'm saying something original here it's
not just that like will be more
decentralized and will be more at home
right but it's also that we have to be
educating not just for knowledge we have
to be educating from wisdom and those
who have to be talking to each other and
meshed up together it's you know a lot
of educational theory you actually the
good educational theory because there's
a lot of crap in educational theory it's
it's untethered from good cognitive
science good psychology it's overly
politicized it's ideologically driven
there's all kinds of some time where I
can see viable stuff is this kind of
sort of core notion is sort of as simple
to say you know if you start if you if
you give you if you begin the early age
project of helping to educate character
and wisdom kids will then be able to go
take in deep kinds of complex knowledge
but if you just try to give them the
knowledge without feeding that human
need for character development and for
wisdom you're gonna find that
many people find that very educationally
challenging and they ultimately develop
a hostile attitude towards their
education in their educational
background and so not only do I think we
need to do it culturally we need to
bring back the education of wisdom with
the education of knowledge I think for a
good pedagogical reasons we need to give
that's very very C deep thinking but I
don't want that to be the state version
of Sunday School where we just
indoctrinate people in whatever
political ideology seems to be in
fashion right now so the difficulty I
suppose I'm trying to bring out because
I think I want to hear exactly to say is
because this points towards another
important point I keep all my questions
are probative because Zack talks about
this convergence right and to me the
convergence is I think the beginning of
the response of a response a deep
response to the question asked how do we
bring back the education of wisdom
within a pluralistic right framework
right exactly cuz it's the world now
it's not a bunch of countries it's not
Christian Europe or world now no I saw
back pointing towards that when he when
he was flagging the necessity of its
convergence between these various
traditions which is not assimilating one
to any master like Christianity
conquering the other ones but of some
kind of like a dialogo so a convergence
is possible and I'm wondering if that so
that struck me is here's how we could
get back to the cultivation of wisdom
within a pluralistic framework yeah and
I wrote about that in your essay you
wrote about a symbolic convergence
between wisdom ages and that's exactly
why I'm bringing this question up yeah
no it's a very good question and it's
it's really one of the more kind of
exciting things that I think will be
coming through education in the coming
decade I think it has two or elsewill
will come apart at the scenes because of
the meeting crisis being like the more
the thorn in the side of the whole
civilization is this this lack of wisdom
starting like seven years old and so
yeah there's as I mentioned the paper a
trans lineage and symbol convergence
across religious traditions and we spoke
about last time something can neo
perennialism like a distilling of some
not essential conclusions that they all
supposedly have in common but a form of
dialogue or like you're saying is an up
ecology of practice which is to say like
a classroom where we can put this stuff
in it and be sure that no matter what
the unique way this kid interacts with
these materials and this teacher that
they will come for their for themselves
to create a kind of wisdom synthesis you
know let's say by the age of 18 right
and so that's not indoctrination that's
actually you know more like a Piaget a
metaphor like a gardening like you make
the resources available with the
container available and then allow them
to grow into the wisdom that's unique to
them and there will be huge pockets of
overlap well they would just be people
like hey I'm signing up for that
Buddhism thing that was pretty awesome I
haven't really found one that's better
or though but people who I'm not really
actually buying any of this I get why
it's important but I'm actually much
more interested a specific kind of
scientific problem but I a rich
humanistic understanding to have my
scientific identity right so we want
that possibility as well so yeah that's
that's very it's very we wanna create a
renaissance person not a person who is
locked in their field correct and
someone who's used to working
with this language and with this symbol
and just working with the idea that part
of being human is having a kind of like
historically an ontological II
positioned notion of self something like
that right that it's like that's part of
if you don't if you're lacking that it's
gifted it's very uncomfortable science
to me you're in the meeting crisis and
that will cascade into legitimacy crises
and capability crisis etc and so yeah so
this is the root of it even if we lay
down the perfect bureaucratic kind of
like technological digital decentralized
classroom thing was all great and we
didn't put this kind of content in it we
could end up with something way worse
we're like more efficiently educating
people away from wisdom and into
technocratic conformity right whereas
what we need to do is like suffuse to
the digital architecture with these
forms of wisdom and it doesn't mean
giving them wisdom it means making the
ecosystem in which when they step into
it all of a sudden they're unless
they're like you know bad actors they
will just by through participation that
will become wiser or at least
appreciative of this wisdom discussion
so yes I think you're John for point to
that oh you're welcome
that's gonna mean we have to I mean
Thomas bjrkman makes this point you
know that we've sort of we sort of
defaulted to that our only Authority is
the market and what we're doing means we
have to because I think the point you
made earlier you know education has
begun has become how to train people for
you know appropriate service to them the
one god that we still all serve which is
the market I'm not a raving Marxists and
I'm not trying to propose the overthrow
of capitalism or anything like that but
what I am talking about is the idea that
we have to have and I think part of what
this can afford us its affording in an
individual's I talk to is a realization
of oh wait there's a lot of things that
really matter to me that aren't you know
aren't coming from or aren't in the
governance of the market and so there's
normative
that makes a call on me that isn't just
the call of the market to produce and
consume again and not denying that we
need to produce or consume I'm not
saying but what I'm saying is the
tyranny of the market and the and and
and the religious idealization of it I
think it's something that's gonna have
to be challenged in conjunction with
this kind of educational reform that
Zack is proposing yeah and maybe that's
why this notion of the digital campfire
or whatever is is kind of coming up even
though I'm not sure if I'm in love with
this term yet because it still seems
that it's a disembodied experience on
some level it's not a real campfire but
but I also like the idea that people
would want to work on this communal
activity together and that might be just
something that people would want to do
right that they yeah is so different
than the alienation of of the market
well that's that's what I'm hoping I
mean I'm sort of talking about when I
was when I was at the store so he was
sort of stealing the culture the way you
know other kind of the wins stole the
culture from you know the you know the
militaristic imperialism of antique
paganism right and and then you've got
you know and and you know Paul Van Dyck
Lee and other people have been talking
about how we we have not forgotten
because it's become second nature to us
how much and a cultural transformation
and that was and so you know there is
this medium outside it's not completely
independent but it's largely outside of
the movement of the market and that this
is a place with the virtual camp firing
where people are finding that the
meaning making and the connection making
and the you know and this this let's
call it chaotic educational interaction
is deeply deeply important to the
independent of the things that they had
previously filled their days with and
that's that's a real wake
I think of a real potential for us you
know because that's what originally
happened you know it you had people
meeting in small groups and they started
talking to each other and then the small
groups started talking to each other and
you can bet this huge bottom up thing
and I don't think it'll go you know
smoothly like some kind of you know a
wonderful home art car can't be made
into a product right okay see made into
a product that I and I fully expected
the way the Roman Empire resisted in
powerful ways this up swelling of a
of a countercultural movement we might
get same sort of resistance especially
by the people who want everything to go
back to normal
we might try to make it into a product
right but but not only that they might
try to clamp down on it they might try
to ridicule it they might try to
undermine it they might try to organize
that and market the slogans and
placement for some sort of a gap or that
sort of get for actually undertaking the
transformation I mean there's all these
kinds of things that I can see I don't
know what to call it you know a
socio-economic system doing our
socio-economic political system doing
well I do think that one of the positive
things that's happening right now is
that people are discovering as this
sounds so trite they're discovering how
really important culture is mmm right
really important culture is and how it's
different from popular culture which is
the part of culture that gets
commodified and marketed right and how
much really important remember that the
center of culture is cultists that which
is sacred right rediscovering how
important culture is the really you know
the cognitive cultural grammar is for us
and I think that is the gives us the
potential you know that this that we
could steal the culture in the way that
we need to steal it in order to get the
kind of I think I can't see how you
would do what Zak is proposing without
doing what I'm proposing at the same
time and saying what do you think about
that I love it I mean
yeah a few things come to mind you know
one of them is yeah when when the world
kind of slips away as it has you know
then you're left with the baseline
values and needs you know and so and
then you realize as you're saying
talking to people long-form
conversations around the campfire holy
crap you know and and the confrontation
with death is part of the realization
because it's not just that the normal
work routines are disrupted and you
can't do your normal schedule and those
kinds of things that it's also that
everyone's worried about death and so on
your deathbed usually you don't say
stuff like I wish I had worked more
overtime you know usually you say stuff
like I wish I had had more family
dinners spent more time around the
campfire right and said more time to get
fired
yeah and the campfire the notion of the
fire the hearth right Estia
I think that's how you say it or Hestia
the the Greek goddess of hearth and
basically the goddess of inwardness and
composure composure and focus and so
yeah there is that returning to the
uncommon afire bowl and realizing that
it's still there and you know to the
degree to which we get used to that it's
ironic a little bit right that we're
supposed to be isolating but I've in my
experience I've been having more calls
and more conversations with a writer or
with a wider range of people than I
usually do and so and most of them have
not been kind of work calls you know I
don't really consider this even like
work like what we're doing here is
actually yeah culture as a way of ultra
the serious poet called the serious play
of culture right and which is
fundamentally uncommon to file and
that's in fundamentally it always will
be even if you just happen to make some
money from it
besides available to everyone it's not
high culture it's not like because no
we're doing PhD level discourse that's
the thing that makes it culture in fact
the seriousness of any conversation
that's being had right now and the ways
that were grappling and kind of like
moving through the the ordeal of it
together with language with commitment
with unspoken agreements and all of
those dimensions that's culture it's not
the artifacts books and all and the pod
cats not the culture the culture is the
living substance that binds us together
and you have to work at its practice to
build culture family cultures right how
strong is it how resilient is it all
those things are coming to life and
that's also what illness does you know
and what death does it it it will
disrupt the routine and basically force
you into being with much most real and
most important and often what's most
real and most important isn't the phonus
stuff it's not the stuff like that's
entertaining and sort of a big stasis
but it is the longest lasting most
meaningful stuff you're going to be
grappling with and there's those
interesting studies on happiness where
it's like it's kind of a little bit
counterintuitive or it's like you know
your everyday experience won't be happy
like you're not gonna be happy every day
if you make certain commitments right
but over the long run you have this
different form of yep contemplatively
reassured kind of like disciplined
well-being which ends up being not a
trite joy or happiness which is actually
kind of inappropriate right now but an
emotion that's the result of being
integrase and authentic and having real
relationships like being fully in solds
the way I would say it down and in your
life which is not a denial of suffering
I think it's in fact the result of it
it's it's it's yeah you know I mean it's
like you you think about
some of the most intelligent wrote this
beautiful essay on war and he was just
like we love for good love for and we
love war because it makes us love one or
not they're all right and we know when
you're in the foxhole
right you're in the platoon or you're
waiting for the soldiers to return at
home and keeping like there's an
intensity to that that's what's
happening now as with nothing yeah and
so more people than kind of like
quote-unquote like embrace the intensity
of it the more that we can find the
substance that these kinds of situations
give us is the substance of real
connections that matter we're like you
know like do I trust you bro you can
trust me like that bond now today means
so much more then it's like on an every
old suburban day you trust me bro eyes
press turbo bus the suburbs who care so
do we trust one another like that
doesn't really matter but now like you
really care dude can i really trust this
person right so the is of love that come
from the kind of the ecstatic ordeal of
the tragic and yeah so we're finding
that and so if we simmer in that for
long enough it's gonna be intense but
there's gonna be no going back because
of what we've tasted now and estatic
ordeal that just quite a phrase yeah
well gentlemen I need to get going
I had a lot of from 12:00 to 1:30 I
really wanted to first of all thank
Andrew for bringing us together again
and you'll send me the file so I can
upload this on my channel as well
because I think this is so I've been
releasing some of our videos together
and do on my channel yeah I saw that
thank you great doing I want to
especially I think Zack for his
eloquently thought-provoking article and
how it afforded this do logos and I'm
glad I got to be a part of it so thank
you very much guys yeah I appreciate
massive appreciation kind of yeah just
gratitude friend for you guys and Andrew
for the stage and and John yeah for your
time and attention I just appreciate it
it's been it's been wonderful
yeah for me um you know this is this is
where I would like to be you know it's
like this is just where I would like to
be the most right at this in this very
moment so it's a way of life that's what
I see today that's fantastic and and the
more and take us because this
conversation has been very intense and
that kind of intensity is is
transformative
I think it's transformative for me and
maybe people who watch it will get a
little taste of that and and you know
and it just a little taste
seems to be very valuable yes